<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two fruitfull and godly sermons preached at Dorchester in Dorsetshyre, the one touching the building of Gods temple, the other what the temple is.</title>
            <author>Chub, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18708)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 192:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two fruitfull and godly sermons preached at Dorchester in Dorsetshyre, the one touching the building of Gods temple, the other what the temple is.</title>
                  <author>Chub, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3]-62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Charle-wood, dwelling in Barbican, at the signe of the halfe eagle and the key,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Chub.</note>
                  <note>Author's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W. Chub, Minister.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two fruitfull and godly <hi>Sermons, preached at Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter in Dorſetshyre, the one touching</hi> the building of Gods Temple, the other what the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Haggai. 1.8.</bibl>
               <p>Goe vp to the Mountaine, and bring woode, and build this houſe, and I will be fauourable in it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by <hi>John Charle-wood, dwelling</hi> in Barbican, at the ſigne of the halfe Eagle and the Key. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull M. George Trenchard Eſquire, one of <hi>her Maieſties Iuſtices of the peace, in the</hi> County of Dorſet, and one of the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Lieuetenants of the ſame ſheyre. W. Chub wiſheth the plenty of Gods graces in Chriſte Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great zeale of good King <hi>Ioſias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 22.</note> and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler care he had in repai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the Temple of God, &amp; maintaining true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, was not onely propheſied by <hi>Id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> 300. yeeres before his byrth, but is now reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred many hundred yeeres after his death, as a moſt worthy preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for all godlye and well affected mindes, for in him was firſt found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, in diſburſing money toward the building therof, then wiſedom in appointing godly ouerſeers to ſee it well doone, and laſt of all care, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſkilfull workmen to doo it, the which godly diſpoſition of his, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb facs="tcp:10400:4"/> the very fruits of a good mind in aſmuch as he wold willingly haue the place erected, wherein the name of God myght bee glorified, and hys lawes &amp; ſtatutes read and exerciſed, and the people of God taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed: ſuch diſpoſitions are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry badges and ſhewes of a feeling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and a godly ſetled minde.</p>
            <p>I may think no leſſe in you (right worſhipfull) but as a ſeconde <hi>Ioſias,</hi> haue endeuoured your ſelfe very care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully for the erecting of gods glory in the Towne of Dorcheſter, my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue towne, in that you haue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ben willing for the exerciſing of preaching in the ſame towne, but haue offred your liberality for the fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thering, continuing, and eſtabliſhing, thereof, to the great comfort of the towne, &amp; no les ioy to the borderers. By occaſion whereof, I was not onely moued with a comfortable minde for my natiue country, to ſee the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of ſo good a purpoſe, but was
<pb facs="tcp:10400:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo bent vpon the ſame argument to preach theſe two Sermons following, which as well in thankfulnes for your proceedinges, as in ſignification of mine vnfained goodwyll, I humbly preſent vnto your worſhip, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to allow of the ſlender gyfte, and to couer the vnwoorthines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with your accuſtomed clemency. And therein, as I ſhall think my pains caſed, my works bettered, and my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell well beſtowed, euen ſo ſhall I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, to be much bound vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your worſhip for your louing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation. And for the ſame ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue mine vnfained hart in faithfull prayers vnto GOD, to bleſſe your dayes with the increaſe of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, to whoſe mercifull tuition I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your vvorships poore coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman ready at commandement.</hi> W. Chub. Miniſter.</signed> 
               <dateline>VVritten in Froome zel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <date>the xii. of December. 1585.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ A Sermon concerning the building of Gods Temple.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ezra. 4. Cap. 1.2.3. verſes.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>1.</bibl> But the aduerſaries of Iudah and Beniamin heard that the Children of the captiuity builded the Temple vnto the Lord God of Iſraell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>2.</bibl> And they came to Zerubbabel &amp; to the chefe fathers and ſayd vnto them, wee wyll builde with you, for we ſeeke the Lord your God as ye doo, &amp; we haue ſacrificed vnto him euer ſince the time of Eſar Haddon king of Aſhur, which brought vs vp hether.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>3.</bibl> Then Zerubbabel and Ieſhua and the reſt of the cheefe fathers of Iſraell, ſayde vnto them. It is not for you, but for vs to build the houſe vnto our God, for we our ſelues together will build it vnto the Lord God of Iſraell, as Kyng Cirus the Kyng of Perſia hath commaunded vs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſte comfortable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> building of Gods Temple, is expreſſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny places of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a notable example how the godly endeuoured themſelues, to ſet vp that place wherein the name of the Lord ſhould alwaies be glorified, and hys lawes exerciſed: not that the ſame place ſhould ſimply be the Temple made wyth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10400:6"/> lime and ſtone wherin God ſhould dwell, for God dwelleth not in Temples made with ſtone, but becauſe God had ordeyned that a place ſhould be erected for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, wherin his Lawes ſhould bee read, publiſhed, learned, eſtabliſhed, and by God himſelfe heard and allowed. And for thys cauſe many the godly kings, as Salomon, Cyrus, Darius, Ioſias, Zerubbabell, &amp;c. endeuoured with all ſtudy to accomplyſhe and erecte it, and which God hath ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaunded, hauing relacion princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally vnto that Temple, wherein indéede his name ought to be glorified, his lawes eſtabliſhed, and wherin himſelfe as chéefe patron, is alwaies reſident, which is our bodye, which by the vertue of our heade Chriſt, is called the Temple. Nowe for aſmuch as the people of GOD in thoſe dayes, were ſpecially knowen by theyr great zeale, paine, and trauel, in erecting that holye Sanctuary, as hauing an one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care for the furthering of holy thinges, (leaſt they might otherwiſe bee drowned with prophane and worldly matters) eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry good and godly man endeuoured to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tt his hand to the building, by which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the godly were diſcerned and knowen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10400:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the vngodly: but ſithence that tyme through the weakenes of mannes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the diligence of Sathan, the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly, (hauing no other credite to afoorde Sathans marchandiſe, and ſathan hauing no better meanes but by woorking hys ſlights and deceipt in the vngodly) they I ſay, haue vnder the pretence of holines, wrought ſathans purpoſe, and deceyued many ſéely yong ones in theſe dayes, as appereth by thys text which I haue now in hand, wherein is ſhewed, howe the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of the Church would haue buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the people of God,<note place="margin">2. verſe.</note> and how they ſought the Lord God, and how they hadde doone ſacrifice vnto him, which profeſſion of theirs, and ioyning themſelues to the people of God to build with them, was but a ſlight to bring their deuiliſh practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to paſſe, as appereth in the fourth verſe following.<note place="margin">Their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> Where it is declared that they diſcouraged the people of God, troubled them in their building, and hired counſellers to hinder theyr deuiſe. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practiſe amonge the vngodly, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende ſome miſchiefe &amp; wickednes vnder the colour of holines, ſuch hath béene the pollicies of all the wicked and vngodlye
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10400:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the beginning, to credite theyr wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked pretences vnder the colour of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. As in theſe appeared, who ſayde firſt, that they woulde builde with them, that is to ſay, with the godly. This is a notable policy of ſathan, to cauſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to bring their purpoſe to effect, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deceiue the weaker ſort by counter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feyting holines, and by making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as it were ſeruaunts of one houſhold, and ſhéepe of one flock: for this cauſe doth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than himſelfe, ſometimes tranſforme him ſelfe into an Angell of light, becauſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious ſhape he wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rather beguile and deceiue, allure and confound, the ſimple true meaning ſorte, euen as the Wolfe by putting on a ſhéepes ſkyn, may the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue acceſſe to the flocke to murther and deuoure at his pleaſure. After the ſame ſort dyd Iudas ſalute and kyſſe hys maiſter Chriſt, which kiſſe and ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a ſigne and token of loue, but it hatched hatred and treaſon<note n="(a)" place="margin">The geſt without a wedding garment that thruſt in among the bidden geſts ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the like effect.</note> I may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well liken them to a great many in theſe dayes, which vnder the colour of comming to the Church, and frequenting the company of good men with fréendly fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and bountifull gifts, doo further theyr
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10400:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> wycked pretences, in ouerthrowing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and confounding religion. In whom hath treaſon appeared ſtrongeſt of late yeeres here in England, but in thoſe that haue béene admitted into fauour. After that they had proteſted great loyalty and fréendſhip? the old ſaying is verified. <hi>In truſt is treaſon,</hi> and in the fayreſt roſe is ſooneſt found a canker. Vnder the coloure of a fréendly quaffyng, King Iohn was poyſoned by pledging a Fryer, ſuch are colours of diſſemblers, whoſe affections are farre from their outward ſhew. Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in a fayre ſhew of Iuſtice &amp; fauoure, could waſh his hands from condemning the giltles blood of Chriſte, and yet gaue ſentence on him, ſuch counterfeyted fauor is ioyned in ſtéede of fréendſhip, and ſuch abhomination in ſtéede of holines, that we may ſay, the wood which they bring is wormeaten, and the ſtones they builde withall is as rubble, not fit for ſo glorious a ſanctuary as the Lords Temple. They haue made eſtimation of their owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more then the Temple of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Agge. 1, 9,</note> which lieth waſte, and yet they ſay, they will ioyne with the true and godly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, furdermore they ſay, that they ſought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10400:8"/> the Lorde, but as they did after a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſort ioyne with the godly, offering to build with them, &amp; purpoſing nothing leſſe, euen ſo now do they ſay, that they haue ſought the Lorde, whoſe diligence and induſtry is iudged the weaker, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not founde him, for no doubt the Lorde is not ſo doubtfull to bée found, nor ſo ſtrange to be ſpoken withal, but that if they had ſought him with faith, and with a harty deſire, they might haue found him. As our ſauiour Chriſt hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſayth. <hi>Querite et inuenietis,</hi> ſéeke and ye ſhall find, and as the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid fayth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119, 2,</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are all they that keepe his teſtimonies, and ſeeke him with their hole hart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deu. 4, 29.</note> and as Moyſes ſayth. <hi>If from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thou ſhalt ſeeke the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt find him, if thou ſeeke him with al thy hart:</hi> but peraduenture if they ſought him, it was (as Chriſte ſaith) with their lips, but their hart was far of, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we behold both their actions that is to ſay, to ioyne with the builders, and to bring nothing to the buidling, and to ſeke the Lorde and not to finde him, ſheweth their bad pretences.<note place="margin">Their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> But now ſée further and behold their profeſſion and relygion, which was, that they had doone ſacrifice
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10400:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnto the Lord, in the which profeſſion and religion of theirs, they expreſſe howe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly and orderly they ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in as much as they take theyr ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall from Eſar Haddon, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sardanapalus, who was Senahcrib, his ſonne who worſhipped the Idoll Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch as his God.<note place="margin">2. Re. 17.26</note> It doth appeare in the booke of the Kyngs, how this people at their firſt enterance into Samaria, and poſſeſſing the Citties thereof, they feared not the Lorde, wherfore God ſent Lyons to deuour them. Then they told the Kyng what happened, who commaunded that one of the prieſtes of the country ſhoulde teache them what to doo, how be it, euery nation made them their Gods, and put them in the houſes of the high places. And this ſéemeth was their ſacrifice vnto their Gods, that they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues had made, euen a ſacrifice agréeable to their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was altogether as I ſaid before in diſſimulation, they were glad that they had caught the verye bare worde ſacrifice, becauſe it was the profeſſion of the prieſts of the law, inſtituted by God, as a figure of Chriſtes prieſthoode, which ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was as farre from their knowledge,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10400:9"/> (I meane of the true vſe of the ſacrifice) as their religion was from good deuotion, or as farre as Iudas differed from an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt diſciple, yet as Iudas gloried of the title of a Diſciple, though he vſed not him ſelfe as a Diſciple, ſo theſe ſpake of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing,<note place="margin">2. Kin, 17. Eſra. 4, 4,</note> yet knew not the vſe thereof, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pered by theyr Idolatrye and diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, enuy, interruption, trouble, and hinde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the godly buildings: but as I ſayde before, ſo I ſay ſtill, all the vngodly from the beginning, haue had ſome ſhewe of godlines, the rather to vtter theyr deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh purpoſes. The maner of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion is, to ſmyle and ſhew a louing coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenance, to them that he wyll ſting vnto death. Honny many times beguileth hym that is poyſoned, ſo it happeneth alwayes with double conſciences, whoſe conſcience is wicked and profeſſion good.</p>
            <p>The prieſtes of Baal and Elias, dyd both ſacrifice, but not alike, nor with the like conſcience, for the prieſts of Baal dyd it in Idolatry and ſuperſtition. Elias did it in good deuotion, and with a pure hart vnto the almightie: therefore the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is true, The hoode maketh not the Monke. Hence is it that pure religion is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10400:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> grounded vppon a ſpirituall profeſſion, and not a ceremoniall ſhew, and hence is it, that we ſhoulde beholde the Lorde in trueth, and vnderſtand him in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not in a profeſſion whoſe ſignification we know not, otherwiſe we might reaſon well, to ſay the papiſts did well to vſe the worde of God in the Latine tongue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the worde of God, but that could not be, becauſe the knowledge and vſe, and neceſſity therof was hidden from men. But ſo is the ſleight and ſubtilty of the deuill, to colour in the wicked theyr wickednes, and deuiliſh pretences, wyth godly titles or godly names, or godly cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies, without the true vſe and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them. The Ammonits<note place="margin">Ammonits</note> did offer and vſe ſacrifice, but howe? moſte filthily and abhominably, when they offered their ſonnes and daughters to <hi>Moloch.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kin. 11.</note> The Iewes did put their truſte in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaying: <hi>Templum domini,</hi> the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, and not in the liuing lord himſelfe, and that with a faithfull harte, as Dauid did in many places, and as is required of all the godly. This is to be no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, that betwixt the godly and the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, the matter is all one, but the manner
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10400:10"/> differeth, for truſt being required of all, is found in all, but not alike, for the vngodly truſt in their Idols, and in ſtocks and ſtones, and the godly in the lyuing Lord, who is theyr maker, preſeruer and gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour.<note place="margin">Iſraelites. Iere, 7, 18,</note> Likewiſe the Iſraelites did worſhip, but whom did they worſhyp? not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hygh and mighty Iehouah, but the Quéene of heauen, that is, the Sunne &amp; the Moone. Why? becauſe ſay they, then hadde wee plenty of victuales,<note place="margin">Iere, 44, 17.</note> we were wel and felt no euill. Such was the illuſion of ſathan, to feede their adoration with a worldly ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour of ſecurity, as though the true bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes did conſiſt in the peace and plenty of this worldly life.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Phareſies did obſerue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole Law in outward ſhewe,<note place="margin">Phariſies,</note> they faſted, they truly tythed mynt, anniſe, and commin, what could the world ſée in them, but the whole body of godlines, but yet Chriſte, who knoweth the ſecrets of all harts, ſaid they were hipocrits &amp; diſſemblers. Who were more deuoute,<note place="margin">Math, 23,</note> and more gyuen to faſting then the Manichies,<note place="margin">Maniches.</note> which gaue ſtraight order for the obſeruing thereof, and refrained from the eating of fleſhe, and yet concerning all other cates and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10400:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> deynties, they ſo porred themſelues, that they cracked.</p>
            <p>And I pray you what greater ſhewe of godlines, charity, humility, chaſtity, &amp;c was there ſéene in our Papiſts,<note place="margin">Papiſts.</note> in al their actions here in England, and els where, they were ful of prayers, night watches, Dirges, and ſolemnities, but in what ſtraunge tongue, and ſtraunge deuiſe, and in what deuotion, the world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, they were ſo full of chaſtitie, that none of them woulde marrye, and yet few but had his Curtiſan: they were full of charity, and yet Tyrants, yea ſuch Wolues, as did daily ſucke the bloode of Chriſt his flocke, they gaue almes plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but they had politike deuiſes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort it from others: they ordeyned &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued many holy dayes, which bredd and hatched many idellers, Idolaters, feaſters gamſters in all ſorts, dauncers, inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent match-makers, and ſuch like abuſes great ſtore, ſcarce was there one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coulde make account of hys fayth, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Goſpell was hydde from them, and all good &amp; godly exerciſes, in aſmuch, as if euer the kingdome of ignorance raig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, it floriſhed in theyr dayes.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:10400:11"/>
            <p>And now in theſe laſt daies, wherin the Goſpell (God be thanked) floriſheth,<note place="margin">Proteſtants</note> and the word of God is dayly preached, we ſée a great many lip Goſpellers, which haue the word of God in theyr mouth, euen from the téeth forward, how they wil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute daily of it, how they wil make choiſe of theyr companies, &amp; yet by their workes ye ſhall know them, for ſome of them are great ſlanderers, backbiters, and ſcornfull diſpiſers of other men, many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great enemies to the poore, ſuch hold the goſpell ſometimes, for the fauour they beare to theyr fréends, ſometime, for the malyce they bere to others, ſome are ſo couetous, that they are become priuy vſurers, and open extortioners. It is a lamentable world, to ſée, in this preſent age, the verye picture of the yong man, that wold learne to enter into the kingdome of heauen, but would not forſake and ſell all that hee had to follow Chriſt. An other ſorte you ſhall ſée, to be like Cleophas, to goe with Chriſt and yet not to know him, theſe are lyke ſuch as S. Paule ſpeaketh of, that wyll come in the latter dayes, hauing a ſhewe of godlines,<note place="margin">2, Tim. 3,</note> but denying the vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and as the Apoſtle ſayeth in an other
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10400:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> place. They ſay that they know God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they déeme him in theyr déedes becauſe they are themſelues abhominable. The Prophet Eſay doth ſharply reprooue ſuch hypocrits, ſaying:<note place="margin">Eſay, 48, 1.2</note> Heare ye this O houſe of Iacob, which are called by the name of Iſraell, and are come out of the waters of Iuda, which ſweare by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, but not in trueth nor in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for they are called of the holy cittye, and ſtay themſelues vpon the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, whoſe name is the Lord of hoſtes.</p>
            <p>The very like hipocrites doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremy recite, ſaying: Run to and fro by the ſtréetes of Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Iere. 5.1, 2,</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nowe and knowe, and enquire in the open places thereof, if yee can find a man, or if there be any y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executeth iudgment, and ſéeketh the trueth, and I wil ſpare it, for though they ſay the Lorde liueth, yet they ſweare falſely. Thus may yee ſée in this briefe diſcourſe, the heape of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, which the church alwaies hath had, and yet hath, woorking vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of holines, by reaſon whereof, they haue not onely brought their miſchiuous purpoſes the ſooner to paſſe, as it is ſayde
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10400:12"/> before, in hindering the building of true holines, but by this meanes the credite and honor of the godly, hath béene emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and oftentimes hadde in ſuſpition, yea condemned amongſt a great many of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different worldlings: wherefore that the one may the better be known from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen as I haue before layde downe the maner and behauiour of the wycked, and theyr hypocriſie, ſo wyll I, as my text leadeth me, lay downe the conuerſation and behauiour of the godly, with theyr profeſſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the one is ſéene &amp; knowne by hypocriſie, ſo the other may bee ſeene and knowen by conſtancy.</p>
            <p>In Zerubbabell, otherwiſe called Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachias, together with Ieſhua &amp; the reſte, fathers of Iſraell was founde this godlye diſpoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That they refuſed the aduerſaries offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red helpe, lothing to ioyne with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They profeſſed themſelues to build to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Vnto the God of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>In the firſt fruit of their good profeſſion &amp; conſtancy, it appeareth, that they allowed not of the offered helpe and aſſiſtaunce of the aduerſaries, although indéede the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10400:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſent occaſion of newe repayring theyr Citty,<note place="margin">Anno mun. 3419.</note> and laying the foundation of theyr Temple, requyred al helpe and aſſiſtance, yet (theyr purpoſe and labor conſidered) they meant nothing les (beeing the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God) then themſelues to doo it, that as the Temple was a place of holye exerciſes, and a miſtery of an euerlaſting ſanctuary, ſo it ſhoulde be erected by none but ſuch as were vnfainedly the Lordes workmen, wherefore this ſéemed to bée a godly purpoſe in the children of God to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe theſe aduerſaries, and not to eſtéeme of theyr labours for two cauſes. Firſt, for that they wexed not faynte nor weary in the trauell &amp; performance of good thinges, dedicated to the Lord. Secondly, that they refuſed to ioyne themſelues to the wicked knowing the inconueniences of a wicked participation, in the which two conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if Gods people doo well conſider, of this preſident ſo long layde before theyr eyes as a good example, it cannot chuſe but be a fruitful patterne, for in that they ſhrinked not at ſo great a labour, but were wylling to doo it themſelues, it is notable for vs to learne, ſpecially in theſe dayes, to doo our godly exerciſes, &amp; labors
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10400:13"/> (eſpecially which are dedicated to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) our owne ſelues, without the care of our owne paynes, or the truſt wee ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in others, and then wee ſhoulde ſee howe the Byſhop ſometimes woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe hys Regiſter, the Iuſtice hys Clark, the paſtor hys ſeruing prieſt, the Sherife hys arrant Baylyues, the maſter hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and ſo foorth of many other profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of great charge, wherein the notable building of religion, and of a common wealth ſtandeth at a ſtay, (nay at decay) for lacke of thoſe that ſhould take paynes themſelues, and not eſtéeme the care of the trauell, whereby the building myghte goe forwarde, for if Zerubbabel and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua with the Elders of Iſraell, had béene lazy themſelues, and committed the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to others being Infidels, the woorke had neuer béene brought to paſſe, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly I am perſwaded, the ſmall care &amp; great eaſe that our chéefe builders haue, is the cauſe that the worke goeth not forwarde, I meane that chriſtian religion is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantially erected, and the common welth ſufficiently ſtayed, but true it is that the labourer, that maketh more account of his wages, then of the performance of hys
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10400:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> workmanſhip is ſo haſty in his labor that the woorke oftentimes ſhameth his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but in ſtéede of ſhame &amp; care in theſe dayes, is planted couetouſnes and ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the one deſireth inordinatly, and the other defendeth impudently. And yet no man can iuſtly charge any Prelate, Magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate, patron or vſurer in theſe dayes, for bribery, extorcion, ſimony, or vſury, and why? becauſe they themſelues committe none of theſe offences, but yet they haue factors and dooers for them, therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede this is their fault, if the building be good, they ſhold doo the worke themſelues, for if the worke be Gods, none is too good to doo it, for that cauſe whom the Quéenes Maieſtie hath thought good, eyther for the roome of a Counſeller, Biſhop or Iuſtice, is committed to the ſame place, to vſe it and diſcharge it himſelfe, and not by ſéelie ſubſtitution. O howe bothe our common weales would floriſh, if our chéefe menne wold by the example of good Zerubbabell and Ieſhua, labour themſelues, and not faint at it. And againe, I wold they wold follow the other example of them, in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them, then no doubt, that muſte néedes be a pleaſant Cuppe of wyne vnto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10400:14"/> the drinker, whoſe dregges are purified &amp; clenſed, ſo that gouernment eſpecially (be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe in them conſiſteth the chéefeſt build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) muſt néedes bee good and profitable, which doo ſeperate themſelues from bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, extortioners, factors, and wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticers, which many times corrupteth a whole country, &amp; hindereth many a good minde. The Lord in any wiſe would not haue his people to ioyne wyth Infidels, leaſt that by touching of pytch they might be defiled.<note place="margin">Eccle. 13, 1</note> The Prophet Dauid ſaid, with the wicked thou ſhalt bee wicked, &amp; wyth the frowarde thou ſhalt learne froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It is dangerous to lay towe by the fire, or to ioyne the Lambe to the Wolfe, for the wycked doo alwaies more forcibly infect, and corrupt, then the good doo or may change or alter, And what felowſhip hath Chriſt with Belial, therefore it is the part of all good and godly men, vtterly to refuſe the company of the wycked, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they wyll offer their labors, and counterfeyte their ſimplicity, I meane ſuch as are giuen ouer to worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in whom there is no hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation and amendment, of whome S. Paule ſpeaketh of ſaying:<note place="margin">1. Cor, 59, 11</note> 
               <hi>But nowe I haue written vnto you, that ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10400:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> not together, if any that is called a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</hi> An other good and godly example they doo ſhew in their ſecond diſpoſition,<note place="margin">Second diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> when they will build together themſelues in the which is moſt notably ſéene &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the vnity of the builders, in that they wyl ioyne together among themſelues, when they goe about a godly purpoſe, and not the one to drawe backward while the other goeth forward, the one to ſtand ſtyll while the other laboureth, the one to ſlepe while the other watcheth, and ſo forth, for that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpynning of Penelope her webb, which was neuer brought to good ende. Hence is it that the wiſeman comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the vnity of brethren,<note place="margin">Eccl. 25.1</note> becauſe it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of a good diſpoſition, and it is the pricke that ſetteth forwarde euery good worke, it is the cauſe that religion is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, the common welth profited, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and vertuous action commended. For this cauſe is it that S. Paule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4, 3.</note> That euery one endeuour to kéepe the vnity of the ſpirit, for by ſo doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the worke ſhalbe both the better and the ſooner brought to good paſſe, for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there are ſeuerall ſortes of facultyes in building, as the Maſon, the Carpenter.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10400:15"/> the Tyler, and ſo foorth, with many other aſſiſtants, euery one of them conferring hys owne profeſſion with the reſidue, in a full entent to further the building, ſhall make the building the better, and bring it the ſooner to an ende, wheras they ſhall louingly conſent together in vnity, euen ſo, among Gods people we haue many or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as the Miniſter, the Lawier, the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the Magiſtrate, the priuate houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, and ſo forth, and euery one of them a workman, to helpe further the building of the Sanctuary. If all theſe doo not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent together in the vnity of fayth, in the hand of charity, in the ſtudy of godlineſſe, not preferring worldly cauſes before hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, they cannot further the buildyng with a beautifull ſhew, nor haſten it to a ſpéedy perfection, &amp; therfore theſe wordes <hi>VVe wyll build together,</hi> be of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and doo giue a good example to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly, to conſent and agrée together, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as the Maſon and Carpenter diſſenting, wyll neuer build well, nor bring the worke to a good ende, euen ſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man in his vocation &amp; calling, ſome in preaching true religion, ſome in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming manners, ſome in teaching a godly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10400:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> life, and euery man in ſhaping ſomething or other for the building of true holines, if they vary or fall at ſquare, they doo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the building: wherfore, as the armes, legs, eyes, féete &amp;c, in one body doo conſent in theyr ſeuerall offyces, to the ſeruing of one bodye, euen ſo euery cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhoulde in his ſeuerall vocation, ſerue in the vnity of ſpyrite to the buildinge of Gods holie Temple, but as I ſayde, if one bee quicke, and an other ſloe, if one buylde vppe, and an other plucke downe, that workmanſhyp wil hardly be brought to good paſſe, no more can it bee wyth true religion, if one be of thys mynde, and an other of that, if one goe forth and an other goe backe. What is it but as S. Paule ſayth, a denying of Chriſte, and a hinderance to knowledge. An enuious mynde, and ſelfe wyl, be great hinderers in theſe dayes, which in déede, doo laye theyr foundation vpon affection and ſelfe loue, and therefore the buildyng can not be good. Wherefore they that wyll bee ſounde, and ſufficient builders, muſt laye theyr foundation vpon Gods worde, and that is the building that is founded vpon the rocke, and wyll not fall by ſtormes or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10400:16"/> tempeſts, as our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth. It is the ſame foundation that ſhall ſtande when heauen and earth ſhall fayle,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> and therefore, all the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Martirs, builded their knowledge &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion therevpon, ſome calling it<note n="(a)" place="margin">Deu. 4,</note> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſome a<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſa 119</note> light, ſome the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom, 1</note> power of God, and ſome<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eph, 6</note> a ſword, according to the mighty working and power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from the which foundation, if any man flée, following his owne wyll or the inuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of men, let him be perſwaded that his workmanſhip is in vaine, for his buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding will not ſtande. The third and laſt diſpoſition of theſe godly men,<note place="margin">The thyrd diſpoſition of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</note> differed far from the purpoſe of the vngodly, as appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euen in the plaine words, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſayd vnto Zerubbabell, and the reſt, <hi>We ſeeke and doo ſacrifice vnto the Lord your God,</hi> and Zerubbabell &amp; the reſt ſayd, <hi>Wee will builde vnto the Lorde our God,</hi> in the which let vs ſée euen the confeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue not the power to name y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord their God, and againe, the confeſſion of the godly in that they hold a firme faith &amp; aſſurance to cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord their God, nowe in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the one by Ezer Haddon an Idolater, and the other by Cirus a worthy and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10400:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> King, it dooth appeare that the one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Idolatry, and the other true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for in that Zerubbabel with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſte builded together vnto their God, which they farder interpreted to bee the God of Iſrael, they ſhewed a good, a deuout, and a godly &amp; chriſtian profeſſion, for as indéede we ought to offer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice vnto God, and put our truſt in God, as the prophet ſayth ſo ought we to haue a ſpirituall care to vnderſtand what he is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4, 5.</note> &amp; whether of right all honor appertaineth vnto him, which we ſhall eaſily perceiue, by beholding hys maieſty, his power, his ſtrength, his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, his loue, his omnipotencye, in creating vs and all the worlde, in gouerning vs &amp; ruling all things, in defending vs, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeming vs, in ſanctifying vs, and in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs, and in giuing all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for vs, in lightning our minds with vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding, in refreſhing our conſciences with good things, whereas on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide, (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgment of Idolatry) we finde not the like vertues &amp; conſolations in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manſhip of mans hands made, to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; worſhipped as a god, no nor in any y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creaturs vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the ſun, moone, ſtars, woods, ſtons, calfs, hylls,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10400:17"/> gold, ſiluer, &amp;c. Wherfore this name God, being an vnſpeakable name among the Iewes, dooth miniſter vnto the godly, ſo many powers and operations, that when they ſhal ſay, <hi>Our God,</hi> they haue a heape of comforts and conſolations in their hart which doth worke many godly knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and exerciſes, and extinguiſhe many ignoraunt and Idolatrous opinions. As for example, if we ſhold reaſon this wyth our ſelues, who hath made vs? and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto preſerued vs? God, who ſuſtaineth the heauens to giue light, and to powre downe dewes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfort of the earth? God, who giueth encreaſe on the earth for our ſuſtenaunce? God, who giueth all things neceſſary for vs here on earth? God, who hath redéemed vs, from the bon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage of ſathan? God, who hath prepared for vs the kingdome of heauen? GOD, the ſame God with hys mightye power, worke ſo in the heartes of all good belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, that they may ſo learne him, know him, &amp; follow him in this world, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come, euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of heauen, they may haue life euerlaſting, to the which, I beſéech God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, the ſon and holy ghoſt, to ſend vs all. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Sermon ſhewing what the Temple of God is.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1, Cor, 6, 19.20.</bibl>
                  <p>Know ye not that your body is the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, which is in you, whom yee haue of God: and ye are not your owne.</p>
                  <p>For ye are bought for a price. Glorifie therefore God in your body, and in your ſpirite, for they are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Temple which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, and dedicated to an holy vſe, for the learning and exerciſing of holy thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for the reading of the Lawe, couenant, and promiſes of GOD, and for the enriching of our ſelues in the true knowledge of Gods worde, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the Sacraments, finally, for all godly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and exerciſes, is the ſame place where in all the congregation dooth méete toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a deuout minde and pure hart, to call vpon God, the creator and maker of all things, to whom he dooth in the power of hys ſpirit appeare, which place is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the Temple or his houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the holy exerciſes, and godly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10400:18"/> which are there doone, and for thoſe exerciſes ſake, &amp; becauſe it is called Gods houſe, it ought to be kept cleane, and not defiled, neyther ought it to be reſerued for any other vſe, then for the exerciſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges:<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.15.</note> and for that cauſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt did caſt out the buiers and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers out of the Temple, yet buying &amp; ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is a lawfull trade among men. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, becauſe of the place it was not allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, but ſhaply and with expulſion reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by our ſauiour Chriſt himſelfe. But now, the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made of ſtones, lyme, and ſande, in this place, but of our bodyes which he cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth a Temple, becauſe of the vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe which ought to be therein vſed, and daily exerciſed, which is godlines, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called the Temple, or tabernacle of the holy ghoſt, wherin the holy ghoſt as a patron &amp; preſident of Gods power dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth.</p>
            <p>And as on the one ſide, euery manne and woman, ſhould in hys hart, reade, learne, exerciſe, and dayly vſe godly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, godly lawes, and godly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, and alſo yéelde the Sacrifice of thankſgiuing, and the offering of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10400:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> and dayly ſtrengthen the ſame with a féeling conſcience, a faithfull hart, a charitable mind, and an humble deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So on the other ſide hath God gyuen hys holy ſpirit to be reſident therein, as a pledge of his loue, which dayly worketh in vs, knowledge, deſire, chéerefulnes, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, patience, loue, &amp; al heauenly riches aſſuring our ſpirits, that we are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, to our great and endles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for which occaſions ſake, we are wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Apoſtle, not to gréeue the ſame ſpirit of God, by the which we are ſealed vnto the day of redemption, for in that hée is dwelling in vs, and remayning as in an houſe among vs, wee trouble &amp; greeue him, when we prophane and abuſe his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle or dwelling, eyther with pryde, whoredome, drunkennes, enuy, theft, mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, idlenes, filthy talke, ſurfeyting, or like, becauſe they are not exerciſes agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the Temple of God, and then, yf buying and ſelling, which is lawfull, bee prohibited the Temple, in reſpect of the materiall Temple, much more theſe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy abuſes, ought to bee caſte out of the Temple, in reſpect that it is our bodyes, being of greater price and eſtimation then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10400:19"/> the building of ſtone. Herevpon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpake in this place, of the abuſe of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fornication, and inceſtuous incontinen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, that it was ſuch a great ſpot, as great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly defiled and polluted the whole body of the malefactor, which was the Temple ordeined for godly exerciſes, and therfore gyueth this ſentence a little before, That he that ſhall defile the Temple of GOD,<note place="margin">Cap, 3, 17</note> him ſhall God deſtroy: becauſe wee are called, not to vncleanenes, but to holines, not to fulfill the deſires of the fleſhe, nor to ſatiſfie the luſts of our carnal minde, but to purge our corruptible man of them, and to adorne the Temple with godly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, that like as the Temple of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,<note place="margin">Hagge, 2,</note> and the Temple of Zerubbabell were garniſhed, the one with godly orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the other with peace, ſo our Temples, I meane our bodyes, ſhould bée decked, and furniſhed with ornamentes, méete for ſuch an inhabitant as the holye Ghoſt is, and the ornaments méete for this Temple of ours, is fayth, loue, truth, mercy, pitty, chaſtity, knowledge, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſo foorth, which vndoubtedly are already ſent downe by God to vs, to garniſh this his Temple in vs, if by our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10400:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> owne diſobedience and wickednes, we doo not defile them, and baniſhe them, but I am afrayd, and it doth partly appeare by this preſent age of ours, that we ſo gréeue the holy Ghoſt with worldly affections, and filthy delights, that wee baniſh bothe the holy Ghoſte, and alſo defile thoſe noble vertues which are giuen vs, as orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to polliſh our Temple, ſo that both fayth, truth, mercy, loue, honeſty &amp; al, are gon to heauen to chalenge the celeſtiall roome, for that the harte of man is ſo defiled with ſin and wickednes, that all the whole worlde is corrupted and ouerflowed with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the inhabitants that now do holde the hart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a dwelling place, which are, diſcorde, ſelfe-loue, carnall pleaſure, and worldly loue, haue vtterly expelled and quite baniſhed, theſe former noble vertues from the mind and hart of man, in ſo much that if we behold them as they are, they worke a great confuſion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of all chriſtian order, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth euery good conuerſation, and are ſet vp as Idols in the Temple of God, for if you looke into the firſt of theſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants or Idols,<note place="margin">Diſcord.</note> which is diſcorde or vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that is to ſay, the iarring and ſecrete
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10400:20"/> malice among houſholders, citties, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and kingdomes, yea euen within themſelues, one detracting and ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an other, one eating vp an other, one ouerthrowing an other, one taking away from an other, one robbing from an other, one murthering an other, and one vndoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an other, it is euen an hel to ſée it, and a lamentable matter to ſée the renting a ſunder of Chriſtes poore members, &amp; the putting of loue and charity to flight, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is that eſtate, that ſhall ſée ſuch an exile. Sathan dooth worke ſo mightily by flatterers, and mens eares are ſo ready to heare them, that diſcorde and variance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quickly ſowen, maketh a ſpeedy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and it is ſo contagious, that it hath almoſt infected all the worlde, in ſomuch, that it is to be demaunded, who is frée from a hatefull harte? or from a dyſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and malicious ſtomacke? and our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſuch, that wee can hardly ſuſtayne it, it is a token that we are voyde of good affection, for when our neighbour or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath offended vs, or treſpaſſed vs a ſmall matter, to the value of one grote, is not our nature ready to ſpende twentye ſhyllinges, or twenty nobles to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10400:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> by extreame Lawe, thys procéedeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuſtice, to be reſtored our wrong, or from patience, as the Apoſtle ſayth, to forbeare one an other, for then we would looke but for a bare recompence or reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, according to the meaſure of the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, yea and that with patience, but it appeareth that we are hatefull and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, when we can not endure a grote damage, and yet can afoorde the ſpending of twenty ſhyllings, thys procéedeth alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from the rankor of ſtomacke. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all thys, the manner of thys preſent world, is to ſtomacke at the happy eſtate of others, who are eyther promoted to wealth, or lyfted into fauour, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them with a malicious hart, iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues (euery man in hys owne opynion) to be as worthy of the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pines, as they that haue it. In this thyng, they obſerue their malice, and looke not into the diſtribution of Gods purpoſe, gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to whom he wyll, and taking away from whom he wyll. God grant that theſe diſcordes doo not admitte our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries boldneſſe and courage, to our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, for if it ſhoulde come to paſſe, I feare mee a greate manye woulde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10400:21"/> pray vppon their ſtomacked neyghbours, bending their enuious harts, rather then theyr country quarrel. The great citty of Numantia, being very ſtrong and popu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lous, was beſieged of Scipid, and he layde ſiedge vnto it a long time, and neuer could ranſacke it, in the ende, the Cittizens fell out among themſelues, and were at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, then theyr force weakened, and themſelues drew not together, by means whereof, Scipio eaſily tooke the Citty, to theyr great ſpoyle and ouerthrow. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt ſayth, <hi>Concordia, res paruae creſcunt, diſcordia magnae chlabuntur.</hi> By concord ſmall things doo encreaſe, and through diſcorde,<note place="margin">Math, 18.</note> great things come to decay. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth. <hi>Euery kingdome deuided againſt it ſelfe, can not endure.</hi> Wherfore, as the prophet Dauid ſaith, O howe good and ioyful a thing it is for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">Pſal, 133,</note> to dwel together in vnity, for that vnity is ſo ſwéete &amp; comfortable vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the dewe that falleth vppon Hermon, and as the hils haue no other comfort but the dewe of heauen, for it hath no run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ryuers to comfort the graſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen ſo, nothing dooth make a more proſperous eſtate among men, then vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10400:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> as it is a fit ornament for the Temple of God, euen ſo is diſcorde a foule polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a filthy ſpotte in the members of men. An other inhabitant or Idoll,<note place="margin">Selfe loue.</note> that is placed in the Temple of God, I meane in the hart of man, is ſelfe loue, a quality or diſpoſition, altogether purpoſed to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettell good order, and to vnioynt the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of man, and to extoll himſelfe, and to throw downe others, this happeneth firſt in thoſe that doo inſatiably ſcratch &amp; heape vnto themſelues, although they take from others to theyr vtter decay, theſe men are vayd of pitty, hard of conſcience, not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, nor forcing the Lawe, if they chance to be touched with the Lawe, they wil alwayes haue a ſhift, eyther to coſen the Law, or to blind the Iuſticers of law, or to bribe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of law, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they doo among the common ſorte of people, in company, pleaſure, ſolace, or trauell, they wyll be ſure, if they be dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of nutts,<note place="margin">How yee ſhall know them.</note> they will reſerue the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels to their owne ſhare. Theſe men are knowen, ſometimes by a fayre flatteryng face, as a Scorpion, ſometimes by gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and making themſelues ſicke, as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab did, ſometimes by a ſuddaine fitte of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10400:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnuſuall liberality, in giuing a cuppe of drinke, but then beware the Fox. I haue heard it reported, that the Fox will tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and make ſporte before the Connies when he goeth about to catch one. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, by a rare fayre ſalutation, as the Iewes that came to take Chriſte, ſayde, Hayle maſter, but alwayes ye ſhal know them by the parting blowe, for though the Cat play and dally with the Mouſe, yet in the ende, ſhe grypeth him to death, and aboue all the markes that I haue ſpoken of, to know this ſort of ſelfe-louers, I hold this the chéefeſt, that is, they vtterly hate and contemne thoſe men, that they be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded they can get nothing of.</p>
            <p>An other ſorte of ſelfe-louers, are ſuch as cary a proude and a lofty mind, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues the ſinguler menne of the world, diſhabling others, and diſcrediting others, to be beſt accounted of themſelues, theſe haue a kinde of ſecrete enuy in theyr harts, for if you commend this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or that man, eyther for wiſedom, honeſty, welth, pollicy, manhoode, comelines, vertue, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or any other good quality, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way he will finde one occaſion or other to diſhable ſome of theſe qualities or vertues you ſhall quickly eſpye theſe kind of ſelfe-louers,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10400:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> either by their ſéelines, or by theyr ſilence, their ſéelines I account, a ſlender wyſedome, or a ſickly conueiance in theyr talke and communication, howbeit, they are full of iolity, and floe with ſuch ſtrang phraſes as they themſelues haue but bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, and are not acquainted withal, the other triall is ſilence, which you ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue by conſenting wyth his diſlikyng, and diſcommending of al men, in thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer qualities and vertues, but then you muſt commend it in hym, &amp; ſo if you finde him either to ſtammer or to bee ſilent vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your commendation, then thinke no other but you haue found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foole, for Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth ſo call them ſaying. <hi>Qui innititur ſuae prudentiae ſtultus eſt,</hi> he that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpon his owne wiſedome, is a foole.</p>
            <p>Both of theſe ſorts of ſelfe-louers are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and abhominable Idols, vnſéemly for the decent temple of god, howbeit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world almoſt is combred with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe preſent daies.<note place="margin">2, Tim. 3,</note> S. Paule himſelfe ſpeaketh of them that ſuch ſhall come in the latter daies, as ſhalbe louers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall An other moſt horrible Idol that doth much defile &amp; prophane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, is, carnal pleſure,<note place="margin">Carnall pleaſure.</note> which is ſuch
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10400:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> deteſtable deſire of the fleſh, as corrupteth knowledge, defileth the conſcience, defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſoule, impriſoneth the mynde, and polluteth the members. It is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh motion, which doth wholy carry vs from God, and ſwalloweth vs vppe in ſhame, I ſay vnto you, it is that thing, as if it were ſhaped, nothing would ſeeme more ougly or monſterous, for it tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth men into the forme of beaſts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the nature of deuils, and therefore, an vnfit ornament for the Temple of God, whoſe reward is moſt horrible, eyther wyth ſhame, or with moſt odious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable diſeaſes, or with extreame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, or with the blotting out of a poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or with eternall damnation, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth. The adulterer and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhal not inherite the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I beſéech thée O Lorde God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to gyue little Englande repentant harts, and féeling conſciences, to purge their Temples of this filthy ſin, Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Worldly loue.</note>There is an other Idoll in this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ours, to whom all honour in theſe dayes is attributed, and which doth onely take away the honor due vnto God, and doth moſt abhominably pollute our harts,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10400:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is, the loue of the world, Thys I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll doth ſo mightily allure, and ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouoke, that it doth wholly rauiſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s harts, and altogether withdrawe theyr mindes, from the true loue of God, from the eſtimation and dignity of hys worde, from the Law of nature, from mutuall loue, from the Kingdome of heauen, and from all other good and godly eſtimations. In ſo much, that we may ſay with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, <hi>Quid non mortalia pectora cogit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſacra fames?</hi> What doth not the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deſire of mony prouoke? It made Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſell his maſter Chriſt, and in theſe dayes, it maketh not onely a great many to ſell their maſter Chriſt, but vtterly to forſake him, it is the prouoker of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure betwixt man an man, it is the ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of theues, it hatcheth coſoners, extor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cioners, vſurers, pillers, pollers, periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, murtherers, flatterers, ſycophants, it maketh offycers and magiſtrats blinde, that they cannot ſée notorious offenders, it cauſeth many to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtry theyr refuge, to the periſhing of many a ſoule by their ignoraunce, it hath diſordered the noble eſtate of matrimony, prouoking ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny to marry for muck, and to like for ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10400:24"/> wheras afterward in hart they hate all dayes of their life. A great many harts it defileth with diſſimulation, contempte, enuy, vncharitablenes, hardnes, and ſo forth. It maketh the ſonne to wyſhe and expect the fathers death in reſpect thereof. It maketh men to buy offices, and ſeeke for dignityes, onely to haue the world, not regarding Iuſtice or reformation, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, and aduantage, which greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth a common welth. It cauſeth many a conſcience to ſhutte vppe his compaſſion from the poore, and it is the onely Porter in rich mens gates, to barre faſt the doore. Many a man ſetteth his ſonne to ſchoole, not for vertues ſake, but for the worldes ſake, many a one preferreth hys Sonne to the miniſtry, not for to preache, but to haue lyuing, many a one preferreth hys Sonne to be a Lawyer, not ſo much to doo equity as to get the world, and ſo of euery faculty, all is for the world.</p>
            <p>Howe many bee there that purchaſe Heauen for theyr children, and brynge them vppe in ſuch order as they may god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye behaue themſelues, as meete mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers for the kyngdome of heauen, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſéeke by all meanes to purchaſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10400:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> the earth for them, howe many ſéeketh to enrich themſelues with the treaſure of the kingdome of heauen? Euery man ſéeketh by al meanes to poſſeſſe the earth, and yet they ſée not this difference, the one bringeth ioy, the other ſorrowe, the one giueth life, the other death, the one ioy and felicity, the other penury, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſicknes, and calamity.</p>
            <p>What reward had the rich man in the Goſpell for all his abundance of treaſure, lands, lyuinges, goods and delicate fare,<note place="margin">Luke, 16,</note> yet in the ende he was rewarded wyth a miſerable death, at which inſtant, hee had thrée attendantly that gréedily gaped for hys death, that is,<note place="margin">The rich man his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors.</note> the executor for hys goods, the wormes for hys carkas, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil for his ſoule, &amp; this was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end and fruit of hys worldly gréedines and inſatiable deſire, ſuch men muſt néedes runne to a bad ende, whoſe beginning and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is naught, howe can that mann haue hys part among the godly, that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies fauoured infidelity. It is impoſſible to ſerue God &amp; Mammon, they haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Mammon, therfore his ſeruants they are to whom they obey, whether it bée of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10400:25"/> ſinne vnto death, or of obedience vnto righteouſnes. Thus I haue briefly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, howe that wee are the Temple of God, and what Idols we haue ſet vppe in the ſame, to the great confuſion of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, if we repent not in time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Second parte.</note>Nowe, as in the firſt part I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you what we are, ſo in this ſecond part I purpoſe to ſhewe whoſe we are. The text ſayth, <hi>Ye are not your owne,</hi> &amp; bryng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the reaſon, <hi>for ye are bought for a price.</hi> In theſe wordes are many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; comfortable conſolations. In that (our vnworthines, and ſtate of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſidered) wee are tranſlated from darknes to light, from death to lyfe, from mortality, to immortality, from a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world, to an euerlaſting worlde, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all ioy and conſolation.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſo much the more is our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in that we are no more our owne, or reſting in our owne power, for if wee were, ſuch were our weakenes, that wée ſhould fall againe to damnation, and ſuch were our inſufficiency, that we could not ryſe agayne of our ſelues, but ſhoulde bée vtterly loſt, wherefore, wee are nowe hys that can ſuſtaine and vphold vs, that wyll
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10400:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſerue and kéepe vs, and who in this life hath ſealed vs with grace, and in the world to come with life euerlaſting, and none els can doo it, or could doo it, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; bleſſed God which already hath doon it And againe, in that we féele the force of ſhine alwaies working in our bodies, and continually ſuffer the tyranny of ſathan, howbeit, it ſhall not bee imputed vnto death, for the blood of Chriſt Ieſus, hath taken away the force of the Law, and the ſentence of guiltines, into whom wee are now graffed and vnited. So that nowe to ſée our tranſlation, out adoption &amp; eſtate to be changed into the ſonnes of God, and we our ſelues as children in his ſeruice, are in a moſt comfortable eſtate, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee are his who will not loſe but preſerue vs.</p>
            <p>Now, in that the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Ye are not your owne,</hi> but that wee are bought for a price, it doth appeare whoſe we are, and who hath bought vs, for we are as I ſayd, the ſonnes of God, and members of Chriſt Ieſus, purchaſed by his precious bloodſhedding, as appeared to the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But now in Chriſt Ieſus, yee which once were farre of,<note place="margin">Eph 2.13.14.15, 16.</note> are made néere by the blood of Chriſt, for hee is our peace, which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10400:26"/> hath made of both one, and hath broken the ſteppe of the partition wall in abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting through his fleſh the hatred, that is the Law of commandements, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in ordinances for to make of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one nowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an in himſelfe, ſo makyng peace, and that he might reconcile bothe vnto God in one body by his croſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t hatred thereby. And as touching that we are not our owne, neyther haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelues but tranſlated into a better eſtate and into a ſurer ſafegarde, it dooth moſt comfortably appeare in Saint Paule to the Romaines,<note place="margin">Rom, 14, 9</note> where he ſayth. Chriſt therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>e, and reuiued, that he might be Lord both of the dead and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, ſo that our ſeruice and all that euer we haue, bee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought by his precious bloode, is ſubiecte to his dominio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and rule, wherin we may (to our great comfort) behold our ſafety; in that we are im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ked in ſo ſtrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tell and defence, as he is, againſt whome the power of hell, cannot preuaile. And in that we are alienated &amp; changed from our accuſable and damnable eſtate, to become (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes of Chriſt,) the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble children of God, in thys co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſteth our
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10400:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> honour &amp; nobility aboue all the creatures that God hath made, which chaunge, we find in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtls words to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Galathians, ſaying, Wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art no more a ſeruant but a Sonne, yf thou be a ſonne,<note place="margin">Gal, 4, 7,</note> thou art alſo the heyre of GOD through Chriſt. It is a moſt excellent comfort, where this alienation or chaunge is founde among men, eſpecially where God himſelfe doth it, for he doth it alwayes for the better.</p>
            <p>Wee finde that the name of Abram, was changed into the name of Abraham, the name of Iacob, into the name of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and the name of Saule, into the name of Paule, the ſignifications of whych named, are bettered in their exchaunge.</p>
            <p>And ſo dooth it happen in vs, in that our exchange is for the beſt, for nowe we are beautified wyth grace, that were deformed by the accuſation of the Lawe, and for that wee are the ſons of God, the riches of grace is beſtowed vpon vs, as S. Paule ſaith, By whome, (that is by Chriſte) wée haue acceſſe through faith vnto thys grace wherein we ſtande,<note place="margin">Rom, 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for thys occaſions ſake, we are called the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god, becauſe we are incorporated by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10400:27"/> grace into Chriſt Ieſus, who is the very pure and vndefiled Temple in whom his father is truely glorified, we had béene a filthy and polluted temple, if we had ſtoode of our ſelues, and depended on our owne power without this gift of grace, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue acceſſe through faith into this grace, hauing apprehended grace, the ſpirit of God doth worke mightily in the faithfull beleeuer. Therefore it is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary doctrine procéeding out of this text of ours, <hi>Ye are not your owne.</hi> For vs to learne and ſée, firſt what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of man is, and what frée wil he hath, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what merite he deſerueth before God. In the which conſiderations, wee ſhall finde ſo great knowledge of our imperfection, that by the view thereof, we ſhal attribute the more honor, glory, and thanks vnto God, who worketh all in all. As touching our power, it is ſo ſmall &amp; ſo ſlender, that wee are not able of our ſelues to thinke one good thought, wee are not able to doo any good thing, wee can not ſtrengthen our weakenes, we cannot make our ſelues to grow, we cannot lengthen our dayes, nor yet can we reſiſt death, neither purchaſe vnto our ſelues life. As the Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10400:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayth,<note place="margin">Iere, 10, 23</note> O Lord I know that the way of man is not in himſelfe, neyther is it in man to walke and direct his ſteps, and as S. Paule ſayth,<note place="margin">1, Cor. 11,</note> what haſt thou that thou haſt not receiued. If man hath any good thing in him, it procéedeth from aboue, as the Apoſtle Iames ſayth,<note place="margin">Iam, 1.</note> Euery good and perfit gift commeth from aboue, whether it be knowledge, life, ſtrength, fayth, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, &amp;c, it is all from God, and by God.<note place="margin">Iob. 7, 1,</note> Iob ſpeaking of mans time, ſayth. Is ther not an appointed time to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon earth? and are not his dayes as the dayes of an hyreling? Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth, we cannot adde one ynche vnto our ſtature. And therfore, as we haue no power of our ſelues, to doo what wee liſt, as appeared by Balam,<note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note> who was hyred by Balake to curſe the people of God, and he and hys Aſſe were interrupted by the way, and were not able to go forth. And as ſ. Paule in his blindnes of minde, was ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with blindnes, and inhibited to perſecute Gods people, wherein his power was weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the ſtrength of hys wyll was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, there is it that Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> Without me ye can doo nothing. Euen ſo haue we no wyll of our ſelues, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualiable
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10400:28"/> to doo any thing, vnleſſe it be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from aboue,<note place="margin">Math, 16, 17.</note> as appeared by Peter, when he made his confeſſion of Chriſte; it was told him by Chriſt, that fleſh &amp; bloode had not reuealed that vnto him, but hys heauenly father. Likewiſe, in the tenth of Mathew,<note place="margin">Mat, 10, 20,</note> our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth. It is not yee that ſpeake, but the ſpirite of your father which ſpeaketh in you And in a great many more places in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures it appeareth that mann hath no power or will at all of himſelfe to doo any thing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it be gyuen him from aboue, and it ſtandeth in great reaſon, and to the godlye ſéemeth very comfortable, for if we ſhould haue wil,<note place="margin">A reaſon why we haue not free wyll,</note> we muſt be free from ſin (which cannot be) whereby our wyll might tend vnto good, or els in this ſtate of ſin where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſtand, how can wee but yéelde ſinne and wickednes, according to the originall of nature, and then is our wyll polluted, and the effect nothing worth, therfore wée haue the helpe of Gods ſpirite, which wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of our head Chriſt, who hath ſent the ſame ſpirit vnto vs, by the which ſpirite, we worke goodnes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, and neceſſary it were, that God ſhoulde haue hys prerogatiue of working
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10400:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> in vs, becauſe he knoweth what wee haue néede of before we aſke, and he giueth bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then eyther we can deſire or deſerue, and his grace is not in vaine in vs for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neither ought we to vſe it in vaine for our parte, and therefore we may bee aſſured of the beſt neereſt and right, when we hold of God and not of our ſelues, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſayde that one heare of our heade ſhall not peryſh, which vndoubtedly is ſpoken becauſe God preſerueth vs, and therefore is God, among many of his vertuous names, called <hi>Adon,</hi> in the Hebrewe, which is <hi>cuſtos,</hi> or <hi>ſeruator,</hi> a kéeper or preſeruer.</p>
            <p>It wee hee that preſerued. Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell from the hungry Lyons, &amp; Sydra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Miſac, and Abednago, from the hote O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: when the Martir Stephen hadde much a do,<note place="margin">Acts. 6, 10,</note> and great diſputation with the Libertines and Cirenians, and them of Alexandria and Cicilia and Aſia. Theſe aduerſaries were not able to reſiſte the wiſedome and the ſpyrits, by the which he ſpake, and thus to our greate comforte wee ſée that the worthieſt worketh, &amp; that is effectuall, if we ſhould worke our wyll, it woulde he ſo weake and ſo wycked, as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10400:29"/> would be accounted nothing worth. And therefore is it, that to our comfort it is ſpoken, that we are not our owne, but his that careth for vs, and hath the ability to prouide for vs, euen the beſt. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs examine our ſelues farther,<note place="margin">Mans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</note> and ſée our merits &amp; deſerts before God, which many haue preached and allowed to the great ouerthrowe of the eſtimation of Chriſt his death and paſſion, as though there were an ability in men to deſerue any thing at Gods hands, which is contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the Apoſtles doctrine, who ſayeth, When we haue doone all that we can doo, yet we are vnprofitable ſeruants. But for the better tryall hereof, let vs examine all our déedes, be they neuer ſo good, as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayer, vnfayned loue, pitty, dayly feeding of the poore, the preſeruing of our bodies in chaſtity and honeſty, forſakyng the world, the fleſh and the deuill, or what els may be commendable in a man, is it able to match one of Gods gyfts? as our vnderſtanding, our ſight, our health, our ſound lymmes, our nouriſhment, our lyfe, our children, our peace, wyth a great many moe bleſſings, can it deſerue any of theſe, nay rather doth not one of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, deſerue and require all thoſe good
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10400:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> déedes at mans hands? yes no doubt, how ſay ye then to a greater bleſſing then all this? who hath giuen Chriſte Ieſus to ſhed his precious blood, to purchaſe vnto vs the kingdome of heauen, and lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting? euen he vndoubtedly, that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be iuſtly recompenced by a ſinful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s obſeruation, and conuerſation, be it neuer ſo holy, and therefore is it that wee are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in debt vnto the Lord, and for that cauſe is it that our Sauiour Chriſte hath taught vs to deſire God in our prayer, that he will forgiue vs our debts, as wee forgyue our debters, and then howe can we deſerue any thing at Gods hands, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we can not make recompence for the ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt things that we haue had already, and doo dayly receiue. Wherefore it ſéemeth to be a very comfortable doctrine vnto vs, in that wee are not our owne, and in that wee are boughte for a price, for if wee were our owne, we ſhould periſh as men that are wicked ſinners, and as men that can doo no good thing, nor deſerue any good thing, therefore of all creatures wee are happy that wee are bought by his bloode, who hath made vs acceptable before hys father, and by whom and in whom, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10400:30"/> is well pleaſed, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſe onely meanes the kingdome of heauen is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for vs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this laſte parte remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for vs,<note place="margin">Our duety</note> and is required at our hands, as duety, that wee glorifie God, which is as much to be vnderſtanded, that we attribute not onely the power, ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, and excellency vnto God alone, but alſo that we ſerue him, loue him, thanke him and obey him, according to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, and that vndoubtedly, is ſo much as can neuer be fully performed at our handes, how be it, ſo farre we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour our ſelues, and ſo farre ſtretch our ſelues, as the meaſure and ability of Gods ſpirite is giuen vnto vs, and becauſe wée ſhould neyther be weakelings in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the holy ghoſt working in vs, nor yet diſſemblers, in outward holines, hauing no inward taſt, we are wylled to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, both in ſpirite and in body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are both Gods, that is, God hath purchaſed them both to ſet forth hys glory in them, as in a holy place or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to glorify God, is (aſwell in ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite as in body) to giue the excellence, or ſuperiority vnto him, and therevppon in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10400:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſame ſpirit and body to all things that are required at our hands, and are beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable for our calling, which is far more to be apparant in vs, then in any other creatures, by how much we are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then they. The prophet Dauid ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſal, 19,</note> The heauens declare the glorye of God, and the firmament ſheweth his han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy worke, which is aſmuch to ſay, as theſe creatures, that is, the heauens and firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doo ſhew their order, courſe &amp; effect, as is appointed them by God, and they do their obedience according to his wyll and pleaſure, the ſunne, moone, and ſtarres doo ſhine and keepe their order and courſe, and haue doone from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, the clowdes haue powred out their moyſture, and yet theſe are not reaſonable creatures, but ordeined as ſeruants vnto man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath appointed them in theyr ſeuerall offyres, they haue performed it according to his wyll. Nowe much more ſhold man ſetforth the glory of God, that is to ſay, to performe that which God wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth to be doone in him, namely, to ſhewe the effects of hys creation, and the effects of his vocation, for he is made a manne, hee ſhoulde not behaue hymſelfe as a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10400:31"/> beaſt that hath no vnderſtanding, eyther in filthy luſt, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwine, or in deuouring one an other, as the Wolfe, or in ſubtilty, as the Fox, or in enuy, as the dogge, or in flattery, as the Scorpion, or in hypocriſy, as the Crocodile, or in ſlothfulnes, as the Aſſe, but to vſe himſelfe as a man, which is a ſtate aboue all theſe creatures, and as we are endued with reaſon, ſo we ſhoulde vary from the brute beaſtes in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of things, that is, to vſe the good and refuſe the bad, and eſpecially becauſe wée are called by God, redéemed by hys ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and ſanctified by hys holye ſpirite, we ſhould therefore ſhewe our ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods power working in vs, that as the Sunne is made to ſhyne, and in ſhyning doth glorifie God, becauſe he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth the effect and ende of hys creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo ſhould man performe and doo the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his creation and vocation, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he hath the power of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and is made the veſſell of holines, and this effect is to liue godly, not onely in outward ſhewe, (as I ſayde) leaſt hee might diſſemble, nor alone in inwarde ſhewe leaſt he myght be fruitles, but as well in body as in ſpirit, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one might
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10400:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> be doone in knowledge &amp; vnderſtandinge, and the other in <hi>facto,</hi> for if the inwarde ſpirite haue no vnderſtanding or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, how ſhall the dum and ſenceles bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is but a corrupt thing, vtter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing els but corruption, wherfore, the glorifying of God in man, dooth conſiſt in true knowledge, in ſure fayth, in perfitte mortification, and in a godly conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſo we might behaue our ſelues in duety to God, in loue to our neighbours, in honeſt and godly conuerſation amonge our ſelues, that ſo much we ſhould ſurpas all other creatures in our duety, behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and calling. By howe much we haue a ſuperiority aboue them.<note place="margin">Math. 5, 16</note> Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayd, Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſée your good workes, and glorifie your father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.<note place="margin">1, Pet, 2, 22</note> And likewiſe the Apoſtle Peter ſayth. Haue your conuerſation honeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentils, that they which ſpeake euill of you, as of euill dooers, may by your good works which they ſhall ſée, glorifie God in the day of the viſitation. So that now, to acknowledge God as he is, and to behaue our ſelues godly and honeſtly, according to Gods will, is to glorify God,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10400:32"/> and to beautify hys temple, in which doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as we ſhall ſhewe our ſelues meete tabernacles and tempels for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, ſo I beſeech God, with the ſtrength of the ſame his holy ſpirit, to clenſe and purge our inward man, from al corruptible mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and deſires, and ſtrongly to defende it from all fantaſies, and illuſions of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that exerciſing all godly and honeſt conuerſations and ſtudies: we may onely be ſetled and eſtabliſhed to ſette foorth the glory and excellency of almighty GOD, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende we may be rewarded wyth the crowne of glory, in the glorious king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of God, vs the which I beſeeche God the father, ſonne, and holy Ghoſt in ſend vs all. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10400:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
